<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>nlp | It's me, Macunha!</title><link>https://macunha.me/en/tag/nlp/</link><atom:link href="https://macunha.me/en/tag/nlp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>nlp</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://macunha.me/images/icon_hu176de0364afaeda8922c372b574c3cbf_6946_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>nlp</title><link>https://macunha.me/en/tag/nlp/</link></image><item><title>Clipping Service News OCR</title><link>https://macunha.me/en/project/2018/clipping-service-news-ocr/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://macunha.me/en/project/2018/clipping-service-news-ocr/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="summary">Summary&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As the owner of the biggest Brazilian media data set, the media monitoring
leader Clipping Service was having issues with scalability, getting close to
their data center maximum capacity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Clipping Service operates on a huge scale, receiving around ~4.5K media press
pages per day from roughly 300 newspapers in both digital and printed versions.
Previously employees called &amp;ldquo;readers&amp;rdquo; were responsible for reading and clipping
(adding highlight into the targeted content) to be later passed onto the
&amp;ldquo;reviewers&amp;rdquo; team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As if the burden of reading countless pages a day were not enough, the readers&amp;rsquo;
operation begins around 4:30 a.m. when the &amp;ldquo;first reading&amp;rdquo; begins (i.e., the
delivery of the morning papers).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="problem">Problem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For over 20 years this content has been ingested by so-called &amp;ldquo;readers&amp;rdquo;. But due
to the advent of the internet and the digital press boom at the end of the 90&amp;rsquo;s,
and nowadays of social media, companies are transferring their clipping
investments to monitoring other areas. Therefore requiring a Clipping Service
action to remain competitive in the market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Through news reading automation using OCR, NLP, and artificial intelligence to
categorize media, the plan was to achieve a higher throughput during ingestion,
giving readers more free time to review the content. Consequently achieving a
higher quality in the content, since we as humans aren&amp;rsquo;t good at doing
repetitive tasks, especially when it comes to reading endless pages searching
for names and words.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="solution">Solution&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="tech-implementation">Tech implementation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>After spending some time researching and benchmarking the alternatives at hand
we decided to use Python as the implementation language for handling texts,
OCR, and NLP (using NLTK). Given its extended API and libraries for NLP and
image processing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the cloud provider we choose AWS due to it&amp;rsquo;s stability and consistency over
other vendors, the conclusion at the time was: AWS price estimative 14.67%
greater than GCP. However, AWS&amp;rsquo;s popularity is greater than GCP and proven in
terms of stability, support, and integrity. Making a safer choice for a
slightly higher price.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The tech stack was: Python 3 using Dramatiq as the task processing library,
running Tesseract OCR jobs, processing text with NLTK and images with Pillow
(ImageMagick wrapper). Redis was the message broker for Dramatiq, a simple
Postgres database stored metrics regarding the execution and we had an
Elasticsearch storing the processed content.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Requests coming from the data center reached an API Gateway, responsible for
executing a Lambda function, and delivering the content result.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best part of the design? We stored and served the content via AWS S3. Each
part was designed with fault tolerance, and we simply turned off the entire
cloud infrastructure after the operation, to turn on only the next day.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Operating only from 4am to 2pm, a &amp;ldquo;serverless&amp;rdquo; and ephemeral project benefiting
from an aggressive cloud cost reduction.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="impact-and-results">Impact and results&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Clipping Service reduced its reading team workforce by ~78%, offering internal
hiring for other areas of the company and a voluntary dismissal plan with
benefits, making the process as human as possible for the former employees.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Using automation for reading tasks, Clipping Service could reach considerable
improvements in the media press ingestion throughput (around 20 times faster),
offering higher quality in press clipping service for its customers and saw the
opportunity in creating a self-service press clipping service later, since the
operational cost decreased significantly.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>