<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>lean | It's me, Macunha!</title><link>https://macunha.me/en/tag/lean/</link><atom:link href="https://macunha.me/en/tag/lean/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>lean</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Matheus Cunha</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 22:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://macunha.me/media/icon_hu176de0364afaeda8922c372b574c3cbf_6946_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>lean</title><link>https://macunha.me/en/tag/lean/</link></image><item><title>DevOps: Benefits</title><link>https://macunha.me/en/post/2019/01/devops-benefits/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://macunha.me/en/post/2019/01/devops-benefits/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Main benefits that a company generally expects and finds in the adoption of
culture:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="faster-and-cheaper-releases">Faster and Cheaper Releases&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Since releases will be continuous and frequent, deliverables will turn into
small changes with the benefit of increasing speed in the development cycle
(delivering always).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="improved-operational-support-with-quick-fixed">Improved Operational support with quick fixed&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If there is a failure during delivery, the impact is minimal because the amount
of modifications is small, just as the rollback is faster. Having a simple
inspection and debugging.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="better-time-to-market-ttm">Better Time-to-market (TTM)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The software will be delivered much earlier when it&amp;rsquo;s still an MVP. Customers
will be integrated as part of the development process, bringing insights and
feedback to the development team. Thus allowing for a higher launch speed in the
market.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="superior-quality-products">Superior quality products&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As has been said before, early failures prevent defects from being delivered to
production, because:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Reduces the volume of defects in the product as a whole;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increases frequency of new features and releases;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Appropriate development processes in teams, including automation.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="now-we-understood-why-lets-talk-about-how">Now we understood WHY, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about HOW&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="continuous-releases-integration-delivery-deployment">Continuous releases (integration, delivery, deployment)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Usually follows a code versioning approach (through Git) using specific branches
for each environment (e.g.: feature branches with git flow).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="continuous-integration">Continuous integration&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Automatic execution of unit tests, integration tests and code quality analysis
against a git branch, to ensure that there was no disruption of the modified
piece of code.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="continuous-delivery">Continuous delivery&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Packaging the software that is tested and approved, to deliver it somewhere that
it is possible to use in a deploy later. Examples are libs delivered in
repositories to be integrated into the code during the next update and code
deploy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="continuous-deployment">Continuous deployment&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Once you have completed all of the above steps, you can do automated deployments
right in the environments, when the team is more confident about the tools they
are testing, as well as the risk they&amp;rsquo;re taking and also understanding that
there is a possibility of failure in a tests environment without worrying that
it&amp;rsquo;s going to be divergent from production.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="configuration-andor-infrastructure-as-code">Configuration (and/or Infrastructure) as code&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To be able to test software with assertiveness, and to understand that it will
transit between environments without changing behavior, it is essential that the
configurations are also expressed in code. This allows the settings to be also
versioned, following the code. Also guaranteeing a uniformity among the
environments, which enables:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Reduction in maintenance costs, having a single point to look at and
understand the operation of the system;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Easy to recreate the infrastructure, if it is necessary to move everything to
another place, this can happen with a few manual interactions;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Allows for a code review of infrastructure and configurations, which
consequently brings a culture of collaboration in the development, sharing of
knowledge and increases the democratization of the infra;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Documentation as code, helping new team members get a faster warm up.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These points were well-stressed by the Heroku team and gave rise to the famous
paper: &lt;a href="https://12factor.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Twelve-Factor App&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s an excellent reading
for the explanation of the benefits of configuration management.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="observability-monitoring-and-self-healing">Observability, Monitoring, and self-healing&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At the end of the delivery process, the software must be monitored. Avoiding to
wait for an external report of failures, ensuring that the actions are proactive
rather than reactive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With mature monitoring, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to create trigger against alerts, creating
a self-healing system in which actions (scripts) are performed to &lt;strong>fix known&lt;/strong>
failures in the infrastructure so that everyone can sleep peacefully at night,
without having to worry about the on-call schedule that makes you read some
documentation at dawn. (If you have had experience with this, you know for sure
how bad it is).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scaling up only those cases that are extreme exceptions (mistakes not
known/expected) in the process for the employee to act, ensuring higher health
in operation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="processes-automation">Processes automation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>All processes that cause Muda should be addressed with automation, allowing
people to work more quickly. Good examples of processes that are usually
automated are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Deployment;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Self-healing (system resilience in response to anomalies);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Renewal of Certificates;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Execution of tests (unitary, integration, functional, etc.);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Monitoring (with auto-discovery);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>User Governance;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="devops-toolchainhttpsenwikipediaorgwikidevops_toolchain">&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps_toolchain" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DevOps toolchain&lt;/a>&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A combination of tools to facilitate the maintenance and operation of the
system, with the flow:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img src="https://macunha.me/img/content/devops-lifecycle.png" alt="Development Cycle Using DevOps" loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: Any similarity to the PDCA is pure certainty.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Plan&lt;/strong>: Project planning phase, in which feedbacks are collected for
requirements survey, and backlog creation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Create&lt;/strong>: Creation of a deliverable (to validate a hypothesis), such as an
MVP;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Verify&lt;/strong>: Pass the deliverable to the test phase;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Package:&lt;/strong> Package the build to be able to put it in some testing
environment;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Release&lt;/strong>: Deploy packaged deliverable;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Configure&lt;/strong>: Perform the configuration of the deliverable in the testing
environment, trying to get as close as possible to the twelve-factor app.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Monitor&lt;/strong>: After deploying to the environment, track business metrics and
infrastructure to ensure everything is working as expected.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>During the implementation of these techniques it is possible to observe
improvements in the development process, the most notable gains are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Increase in team engagement;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Knowledge sharing;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reduction of bottlenecks;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>More free time to do work that really matters (adds value to the user
experience or generates impact);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Greater confidence in delivering software.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>DevOps: The Genesis</title><link>https://macunha.me/en/post/2019/01/devops-genesis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://macunha.me/en/post/2019/01/devops-genesis/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>First of all, it&amp;rsquo;s all about agile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The DevOps methodology was created on top of agile methods, to deliver a higher
value inside software releases, automating feature release through pipelines,
that can test hypothesis faster allowing higher adaptability using &amp;ldquo;fail-fast&amp;rdquo;
approaches. Those changes are more cultural than technical, so it&amp;rsquo;s normal to
see DevOps being called culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The implementation of DevOps happens through processes automation, having a
strong sense of processes re-engineering inside the company. Comparing to the
cultural change, the technical is easy to implement. Therefore the role that a
&amp;ldquo;DevOps Engineer/Analyst&amp;rdquo; performs is very confusing, which enables many
SysAdmins and Infra Analysts assuming the role of &amp;ldquo;DevOps.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="lean-is-the-basis-of-agile">Lean is the basis of Agile&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Reality is not as happy as it sounds. After World War II, Japan was destroyed
and under-resourced after losing the war. With a limited amount of resources,
the country needed to reinvent itself and survive after a time of severe
depression. During that time two guys gained attention inside a company that
later gave its name after the methodology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Those guys were Eiji Toyoda and Taiichi Ohno, inside Toyota Motor Corporation.
They&amp;rsquo;re the founders of the &amp;ldquo;Toyota production model&amp;rdquo; also known as Toyotism.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="toyota-gave-birth-to-lean">Toyota gave birth to Lean&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Lean teaches how to optimize the end-to-end process, focusing on processes that
create value for customers. Bottlenecks in the process must be removed, and
wasteful activities need to be identified and avoided. Both explained and
defined by LEAN 3M: Muda, Mura, and Muri.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also teaches to improve yourself day after day and always focus on quality
through Kaizen (continuous improvement).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Japanese culture truly believes that quality is the main objective to deliver
value to customers since quality is what brings your clients back.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="kaizen">Kaizen&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A mindset that helps to look at each part of the process exclusively and think
about the improvements. Involving the people who are part of the process,
encourage the inclusion of these people in the decisions of change, since:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It is much easier to accept a change when it is not imposed (top-down);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is a greater absorption of change by people when they&amp;rsquo;re included in the
planning;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The people who are involved in the process bring their concerns and
suggestions, which contribute positively to the evolution of the change,
making the idea more robust.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The process of defining improvements through Kaizen happens (usually) in the
following order:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Define data-driven objectives;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Review the current state and develop an improvement plan;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Implement improvement;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Review the implementation and improve what does not work;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Report the results and determine the items to be monitored.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This process is also called &lt;strong>PDCA: Plain-Do-Control-Act&lt;/strong>, which is summarized
in:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Plan (develop the hypothesis);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do (experiment);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check (validate results);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Act (refine the experiment and start over).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="3m-muda-mura-muri">3M: Muda, Mura, Muri&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="muda-waste">Muda (waste)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Any activity that consumes time without adding value to the final consumer. e.g.:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>over-production;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>idle time in the process;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>products with a defect.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that there are different levels of Muda that can be
removed quickly or not, and the classification depends on the time for removal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An example of a more time-consuming Muda is the discontinuation of legacy
software that ends up with longer release cycles, causing teams to be idle,
followed by an often long or manual test routine.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="mura-unevenness">Mura (unevenness)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Unevenness in operation, caused by activities that are very changeable and
unpredictable, generating different results in all executions. e.g., the
execution of tasks that were not well planned and ended up arriving with strict
deadlines. The team runs in the rush, generating exhaustion, despair, and
moreover, when finished leaves the people who have performed these tasks waiting
(for feedback, or confirmation that it is completed).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="muri-overload">Muri (overload)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Overburdening equipment or operators by requiring them to run at a higher or
harder pace beyond the limit, to achieve some goal or expectation, causing
fatigue and consequently failures during the process. These failures are usually
human errors caused by fatigue during overwork.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="back-to-agile">Back to Agile&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In 2000 a group of 17 people met at a resort in Oregon to talk about ideas that
could improve the flow of software development. After a year of mature ideas,
these people met again and published the ideas, which we now know as &lt;strong>Agile
Manifesto&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Main points are:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Individuals and interactions&lt;/strong> over processes and tools &lt;strong>Working software&lt;/strong>
over comprehensive documentation &lt;strong>Customer collaboration&lt;/strong> over contract
negotiation &lt;strong>Responding to change&lt;/strong> over following a plan&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will restrict the explanation of these points with the DevOps point of view,
keeping on track (now).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="individuals-and-interactions">Individuals and interactions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>over processes and tools&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First comes the individuals, they should receive the necessary tooling to work
with, and then be empowered to do their jobs. Interactions between people are
greatly encouraged, for sharing knowledge and also for facilitating creative
flow within development teams.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An excellent example of interaction encouraged through DevOps is the code review
habit. Considering that small parts of the software will be iterated and
approved in the pipeline passing through different environments, automatically,
the best way to prevent defects is through code review.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This habit brings benefits such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Knowledge sharing;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Observation of the problem from a different point of view;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Team engagement;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lesser bugs.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="working-software">Working software&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>over comprehensive documentation&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s a trick in &amp;ldquo;working software,&amp;rdquo; software that works is not code that
compiles. The software that works is what meets the requirements of the user;
i.e., the software that solves the problem and the pains of the user.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the market is very dynamic, and evolves with high speed, often during the
software development project the requirements change due to external factors.
Therefore, knowing that it is not possible to predict all the elements, many
&amp;ldquo;workarounds&amp;rdquo; are made during development and documented. Passing the
responsibility to the user to handle the faults, and perform the workarounds,
expending more effort than would be required to perform the tasks using the
software.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Deliver a working software frequently, ranging from a few weeks to a few months, considering shorter time-scale. - Agile Manifesto&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Encouraging as many deployments as possible, so that failures happen as early as
possible, thus allowing their impact to be much less.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="fail-fast">Fail-fast!&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Failures are understood and encouraged because it&amp;rsquo;s part of the mindset. Because:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Only those who &lt;strong>do&lt;/strong> make mistakes;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Failures are the best opportunity for learning and evolving;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shit happens.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Nothing like quoting Murphy&amp;rsquo;s law to contextualize&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Anything that can possibly go wrong, does.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Therefore, it&amp;rsquo;s best for failures to occur early, while the cost of correction
is still low. Failing a controlled testing environment allows the fix to be much
faster (and cheaper) than it would if the fix were already in production.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this approach to succeed, there is a premise that environments are
production copies, or at least as close as possible. Otherwise, there will be
behavioral changes in the software between the environments, making the test
environment unfeasible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the environments are divergent, the promotion of bugs for production will be
very frequent, causing late failures, which are expensive failures.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="customer--collaboration">Customer collaboration&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>over contract negotiation&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Know your client! Including it in the process is the best approach to have
working software. After iterating over deliverables, it&amp;rsquo;s essential to create a
positive feedback loop with your client, bringing it as close as possible to the
development of the tools that he/she is going to use.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can describe this situation with:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>From point A it is possible to see only point B;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>From point B it is possible to see point C;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Therefore there is a great incentive for the software to be delivered in parts,
continuously. Thus gathering user feedback on the next steps, following the
concepts of evolutionary prototyping, which were widely publicized through &lt;a href="http://theleanstartup.com/book" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;em>The
Lean Startup&lt;/em>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This point contrasts sharply with the previous one about continuous release, so
that it is possible to present the prototype and evolve it throughout the
project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Learn who your customer/consumer/user is, and whom you are making the software
for, as this is the only way you can deliver value to that customer. An
essential part of the software development process is to be empathic with user
problems, and to truly understand what the problem is to be solved, and the
result of the impact on software development (value creation for the user).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="responding-to-change">Responding to change&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>over following a plan&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Redesigning the requirements overtime is part of the job, and a necessary step
to success. If you want to build something useful that is going to grow and have
absorption, it&amp;rsquo;s a key feature to include your client in the implementation
process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It will be the only way to bring all the problems of the user to the table and
create the best solution for all these problems because the user is the only
person that knows the real challenges he faces in their routine dealing with
software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With continuous delivery of software along with monitoring results, the process
of collecting feedback is much simpler and faster.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="devops-devops-devops">DevOps, DevOps, DevOps&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>With the popularization of DevOps, a lot of disagreement came out there followed
by a significant confusion about the subject. It is very common to come across
different interpretations of &lt;strong>what is DevOps&lt;/strong>. There is a lot of euphemism in
the area, and gourmetization on LinkedIn, with many SysAdmins calling themselves
DevOps since they learned to code shell script inside Python.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Do you want to keep reading? &lt;a href="https://macunha.me/en/post/2019/01/devops-benefits/">Here are the benefits of adopting DevOps techniques.&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>